<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | ROSSyndicate</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/</link><atom:link href="https://rossyndicate.com/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://rossyndicate.com/media/icon_hu4fef5532944d6df354a8eec30a0a86cc_1217210_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/</link></image><item><title>Life After Fire</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/life_after_fire/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/life_after_fire/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="this-workshop-series-will-make-transdisciplinary-connections-amongst-scientists-researching-the-environmental-impact-of-the-largest-wildifres-in-colorado-history-and-engage-the-public-with-their-findings." class="section level2">
&lt;h2>This workshop series will make transdisciplinary connections amongst scientists researching the environmental impact of the largest wildifres in Colorado history and engage the public with their findings.&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the Cameron Peak and East Troublesome Fires burned more than 400,000 acres of land west of Fort Collins, Colorado State University scientists and their local partners have been researching their direct impacts on our environment.The ROSSyndicate and the Geospatial Centroid at CSU are hosting a three-series event to hear directly from ~10 different research teams as they assess the effects of these catastrophic, high-elevation wildfires on local fisheries, water quality, water quantity, and ecosystem recovery. These workshops have two aims, 1) promote collaboration across scientific disciplines so we can better understand and respond to these fire events in the future and 2) engage the public with these findings.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>AquaSat</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/aquasat/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/aquasat/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="building-a-robust-living-matchup-dataset-that-pairs-remote-sensing-imagery-with-water-quality-samples." class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Building a robust, living matchup dataset that pairs remote sensing imagery with water quality samples.&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reliable, reproducible, and timely estimates of inland water quality from remote sensing can provide foundational insight to improve water management decisions, empower stakeholders to monitor their waterbodies, and help scientists better understand how inland waterbodies are changing. However, using remote sensing to produce robust estimates of key water quality parameters like chlorophyll a (a proxy for algal biomass), sediment concentrations, dissolved organic carbon, and overall water clarity requires a harmonized, clean, and analysis-ready ground-truth dataset. One such dataset is AquaSat, a database of more than 600,000 “matchups” that pair in-situ water quality grab samples with surface reflectance data from Landsat 5, 7, 8 data over the Continental United States (Ross et al. 2019). The purpose of the proposed work is to dramatically expand and improve AquaSat in three crucial ways. First, we will incorporate more in-situ data from water quality sensors, optically inactive constituents like nutrients, and more data sources from the Water Quality Portal and additional data sources (e.g., LAGOS USA; Soranno et al. 2015). Second, we will create a data quality tiering system to address issues in the original dataset: restrictive-data that is verifiably self-similar across organizations and time-periods and can be considered completely interchangeable; narrowed-data that we have good reason to believe is self-similar, but for which we can’t verify full harmony across data providers; inclusive-data, the current level of data provided by AquaSat, where data are assumed to be reliable and harmonized unless obvious differences exist. Third, we will add new satellites and spectral bands to our matchup database, including Sentinel-2, MODIS-AQUA, and Sentinel-3. All of these additional satellites or constellations of satellites have potential use for remote sensing of water quality, and this new work will add them to the AquaSat database. These improvements, along with tutorials and workshops developed by the project, will enable USGS, NASA, and academic researchers to more easily and reliably observe water quality patterns at unprecedented spatial and temporal scales.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>NASA - Illinois and Ohio River Watersheds</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nasa_il_oh/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nasa_il_oh/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="how-and-why-do-algae-blooms-move-through-river-and-reservoir-networks" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>How and why do algae blooms move through river and reservoir networks?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Understanding and predicting algal blooms in river systems requires a “network” perspective that takes into account hydrologic connectivity as well as variability in dominant controls over blooms such as river discharge, temperature, sunlight, and nutrients. No one approach-satellite observations, in-situ sensors, or modeling-can be used to both measure algal blooms and quantify the antecedent bloom conditions over both time and space. Therefore, we propose to close major methodological and conceptual gaps in remote sensing, machine learning modeling, and understanding algal blooms in rivers and reservoir using a cutting-edge monitoring platform that will provide chlorophyll-a (chl-a) observations (a proxy for algal blooms) at the spatial and temporal density required to understand why, where, when, and how riverine and river/reservoir algal blooms occur. To accomplish this goal we will produce daily estimates of chl-a by fusing continuous sensor, grab sample, and environmental driver data (e.g. discharge, temperature, climate etc.) with Landsat OLI and Sentinel-2 observations of chl-a within a hydrologic-network-aware Process Guided Deep Learning model (PGDL, Jia et al., 2021). Our objectives include,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>Build chl-a database across all rivers/reservoirs using satellite imagery. 2&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Develop PGDL model fusing in-situ and satellite data to generate chl-a database with a daily temporal resolution and spatial resolution equal to the National Hydrography Database to identify algal bloom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Interpret PGDL model to identify the antecedent conditions over time and space that lead to algal blooms.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>We focus on two bloom-prone systems: the Ohio River Basin and the Illinois River Basin. These are ideal locations to develop and test our approach since the Illinois Basin is a focal area for USGS Next Generation Observing System focused on blooms, and the Ohio River is relatively data sparse to test transferability of our approach. Our overarching science question is: what are the antecedent conditions over time and space that are linked to algal bloom occurrence and severity in rivers and reservoirs?&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>NASA - Water Resources</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nasa_wr/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nasa_wr/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="how-can-remote-sensing-and-data-fusion-help-water-resource-managers" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>How can remote sensing and data fusion help water resource managers?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The objective of this proposal is to overcome historic barriers that prevent water resources managers from using remote sensing into decision making process of water resource management in Northern Colorado (Fig. 1). To accomplish this task, we will build on existing collaborations with: Northern Water and the cities of Fort Collins and Greeley, who, together, supply wate to over 1 million residents in Northern Colorado. However, like most of the Western United States, these water supplies are dually threatened by impacts to water quantity and quality. Harmful algae blooms, increased sedimentation of supply reservoirs and highly varying concentrations of dissolved organic carbon, can all interfere with a water suppliers ability to provide clean drinking water to their customers. Here, We propose a project to use machine learning, remote sensing, and live-streaming sensors to build a system that predicts water quality at seasonal and weekly timescales.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>National Park Service Water Scarcity</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nps/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/nps/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="how-vulnerable-are-us-national-parks-to-water-scarcity" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>How vulnerable are US National Parks to water scarcity?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project will evaluate the influence of climate change on the security of National Park Service water supplies, beginning with parks in hydrologic settings most likely to experience supply challenges. If a water supply is found to be sensitive to climate change and projected to experience climate-related changes that will impair the supply’s quantity and/or quality, adaptation actions can be undertaken to further secure that water supply (e.g., increase water conservation at the site, reduce existing losses in water transmission, increase water storage, etc.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Sensors</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/sensors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/sensors/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="what-is-the-value-of-individual-sensors-in-river-networks" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>What is the value of individual sensors in river networks?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is an increasing interest to install dense networks of sensors in stream networks to help predict flow and water quality - but the questions of how many sensors and where is an open question. This project aims to link the strengths of a deep learning model and a physics-based model to quantify the value of each new sensor in the river network. This work will help inform stakeholders decide where to implement new sensors in a monitoring network to maximize the value for model predictions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Macrosheds</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/macrosheds/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/macrosheds/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="using-data-science-to-enable-continental-scale-watershed-synthesis." class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Using data science to enable continental-scale watershed synthesis.&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cuahsi.shinyapps.io/macrosheds/">Macrosheds&lt;/a> aims to massively increase the access, use, and analysis of watershed ecosystem data by merging all US watershed ecosystem studies into a common data platform, and by building high-powered data infrastructure and visualization tools around it. This platform will also be used to grow the next generation of watershed scientists through our macro-scale watersheds training camps. Macrosheds is currently being used to investigate and visualize big questions like what types of watersheds are best at retaining nutrients, recovering most rapidly from decades of acid rain, have the highest erosion rates, and have flow patterns that are least sensitive to floods and droughts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Macrosheds is an NSF funded project and is co-investigated with the &lt;a href="https://bernhardtlab.weebly.com/">Bernhardt Lab&lt;/a> at Duke University.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Upper Poudre</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/upper_poudre/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/upper_poudre/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="how-do-wildfires-affect-water-quality-and-algal-growth-in-high-elevation-reservoirs-and-are-those-changes-propagated-downstream" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>How do wildfires affect water quality and algal growth in high elevation reservoirs, and are those changes propagated downstream?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The 2020 Cameron Peak wildfire (CPF) was the largest wildfire in Colorado history at over 200,000 acres. The CPF burned a large proportion of the Cache La Poudre watershed, in particular various high elevation reservoirs. These reservoirs provide valuable drinking and agriculutural water to users in the City of Fort Collins, Greeley, Thornton and Northern Water. In collaboration with the Rocky Mountain Research Station (USFS), we are sampling various reservoir, tributary, and mainstem sites of the Cache La Poudre watershed. This field campaign allows us to analyze trends in water quality focusing on nutrients and other key constituents mobilized post-fire. The goal of this project is to understand how these nutrients affect algal growth in reservoirs and how those changes are felt downstream. Using this field data, we are working to create a system that will predict algal blooms before they occur using a combination of in-stream sensors, remote sensing, and field sampling.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Lower Poudre</title><link>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/lower_poudre/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rossyndicate.com/projects/lower_poudre/</guid><description>
&lt;div id="how-does-the-cache-la-poudre-river-change-as-it-travels-through-fort-collins-colorado" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>How does the Cache la Poudre River change as it travels through Fort Collins, Colorado?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Cache la Poudre River Monitoring Network is a collection of river monitoring sites strategically located throughout and directly upstream of the City of Fort Collins. Established in 2019, this network represents a unique public-private partnership between the City’s storm water and water quality divisions, the ROSSyndicate, and In-Situ Inc., a water monitoring equipment manufacturer based in Fort Collins. This monitoring partnership was spurred by the 2018 fish kill through the city, whose source was never determined. With a network of sensors now deployed, we can better track changes in water quality like those experienced in 2018 and understand how the river is influenced by its myriad of urban and agricultural inputs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>